The video I'm about to show is the first time that I'm seeing any of the hunger strikers mentioned on mainstream news in any kind of detail, even if those details are wrong and skewed. Allow me to help.
A Palestine action activist who's been on a 46-day hunger strike in prison has been taken to hospital after a condition deteriorated.
Well, that makes it sound like the oh-so-benevolent prison staff at HMP Brunsfield just called the ambulance, but that's not true. Activists and even MP Zahra Sultana had to protest outside to get the prison to finally call and allow for an ambulance to take Kesa to hospital.
Kesa Zahra was in HMP Brunsfield awaiting trial over an alleged break-in as an Israel-based defence firm.
An alleged break-in, not an act of terrorism, yet counter-terrorism powers have been used against them.
And it's not a defence firm, it's a weapons manufacturer called Elbert Systems, and it operates on British soil making drones that are used to kill Palestinians.
Jane Deeth joins me now with more on this. Jane.
Yes, Kesa Zahra has been refusing food for almost two months now. She's waiting to be tried over the alleged break-in at the defence company.
Weapons manufacturer.
She joins five other prisoners refusing food.
There are actually seven other hunger strikers. Kesa is one of eight.
Some charged also in connection with the defence company.
Weapons manufacturer.
Others accused of breaking into RAF Bryce Norton.
Their collective refusal of food is believed to be the biggest hunger strike since 1981, the IRA hunger strike in the Mays prison, where 23 prisoners refused food,
and 10 of them starved themselves to death.
Starved themselves to death removes any blame from the British government for not engaging with a very reasonable demand of wanting to be recognised as political prisoners,
which they were, and the Filton 24 clearly are.
The lawyers for these activists say that they were charged before Palestine action was banned by this government under terrorism legislation.
But nonetheless, they claim that since the group was prescribed, they faced harsher treatment in prison,
saying they'll all face over a year in prison before they get to any trial and that their communications have been restricted.
People can be held on remand for a maximum of six months.
There is a possibility to extend it if it is absolutely necessary.
But for an alleged break-in, even six months would be extreme.
What they're demanding is that they are all immediately released on bail.
This afternoon, dramatic events, Kesa Zura did leave HMP Bronzefield, but in an ambulance, critically ill, her supporters say.
I spoke to a friend of hers, Ella, who said that she spoke to Kesa yesterday evening,
who reported being so weak she was unable to stand, and claims that she was asking for that ambulance yesterday.
Asking for an ambulance for an entire day, but it only arrived once activists took action outside of the prison.
Had they not done that, it is very possible that the prison would have left Kesa to die in her cell.
What's the government saying?
Well, I spoke to the Ministry of Justice this evening who told me that prisoners who refuse food are continually assessed by prison healthcare staff
who do take appropriate action, including arranging hospital treatment when it's required.
Clearly that didn't happen.
So far, David Lammy...
Absolute waste, man.
...has not granted the request to meet the lawyers and MPs of the six people on hunger strike,
but the government says he is being kept informed of the situation.
Oh, fantastic.
So no need for us to worry.
Follow Prisoners for Palestine to stay updated and share and amplify the voices of the hunger strikers
and the family, friends and activists, bringing awareness to them,
as we can't trust the media to do so in any honest fashion.
Love ya.